<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc authorship="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-paw-use-cases-00">


<front> 

    <title abbrev="PAW use cases scenarios">
    
    </title>
   
   
 
	<author initials="G.Z." surname="Papadopoulos" fullname="Georgios Papadopoulos">
    	<organization>IMT Atlantique</organization>
    	<address>
        	<postal>
            	<street>Office B00 - 114A</street>
             	<street>2 Rue de la Chataigneraie</street>
             	<city>Cesson-Sevigne - Rennes</city>
             	<code>35510</code>
             <country>FRANCE</country>
         	</postal>
         	<phone>+33 299 12 70 04</phone>
         	<email>georgios.papadopoulos@imt-atlantique.fr</email>
		</address>
	</author>
 
 	<author initials="P" surname="Thubert" fullname="Pascal Thubert">   
		<organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
      	<address>
        	<postal>
            	<street>Building D</street>
            	<street>45 Allee des Ormes - BP1200 </street>
            	<city>MOUGINS - Sophia Antipolis</city>
            	<code>06254</code>
            	<country>FRANCE</country>
         	</postal>
         	<phone>+33 497 23 26 34</phone>
         	<email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>   
 
	<author initials="F." surname="Theoleyre" fullname="Fabrice Theoleyre">
    	<organization>CNRS</organization>
     	<address>
        	<postal>
            	<street>Office B-270</street>
             	<street>Boulevard Sebastien Brant</street>
             	<city>Illkirch</city>
             	<code>67400</code>
             	<country>FRANCE</country>
         	</postal>
         	<phone>+33 368 85 45 33</phone>
         	<email>theoleyre@unistra.fr</email>
     	</address>
 	</author>


   <date/>

   <workgroup>PAW</workgroup>

   <abstract>
   <t>
       blablka
   </t>
   </abstract>
   

</front>

<middle>



<!--section title="TEMPORARY EDITORIAL NOTES">

   <t>
		This document is an Internet Draft, so it is work-in-progress by nature.
   		It contains the following work-in-progress elements:
   </t>	
     		 
   <t>
   	<list style="symbols">
		<t>"TODO" statements are elements which have not yet been written by the authors 
		for some reason (lack of time, ongoing discussions with no clear consensus, etc).
		The statement does indicate that the text will be written at some time.</t>
   	</list>
   </t>
   		 
</section --> 



<section title="Introduction">

    <t>
    Based on time, resource reservation, and policy enforcement by distributed 
	shapers, Deterministic Networking provides the capability to carry
	specified unicast or multicast data streams for real-time applications with
	extremely low data loss rates and bounded latency, so as to support
	time-sensitive and mission-critical applications on a converged enterprise
	infrastructure.  
	</t>
	<t>
    Deterministic Networking technology allows new Quality of Service (QoS)
	guarantees of worst-case delivery.  More precisely, the worst-case data
    latency can be guaranteed for a bounded throughput in a consistent fashion
	as multiple	services are deployed, augmenting the load of the network with
	no measurable impact on existing flows whatsoever. Additional QoS goals can
	include a loss ratio like 10e-5 or a maximum losses in a row like three
	consecutive losses at a maximum.
	</t>
	<t>
	Key attributes of Deterministic Networking are:
       <list>
     <t> Time synchronization on all the nodes, often including source and destination </t> 
	 <t>The centralized computation of network-wide deterministic paths</t>
	 <t>New traffic shapers within and at the edge to protect the network</t>
     <t>Specialized hardware for scheduled access to the media.</t>
	   </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	So far, Open Standards for Deterministic Networking have prevalently been
	focused on wired media, with Audio/Video Bridgeing (AVB) and Time Sensitive
	Networking (TSN) at the IEEE and DetNet <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-architecture"/> at the IETF. But in a number of
	use-cases, wires can simplu not apply. Examples include mobile or rotating
	devices, rehabilitated industrial buildings, wearable or in-body sensory
	devices, vehicle automation and	multiplayer	gaming.
	</t>
	<t>
	Purpose-built technologies <xref target="ISA100"/>
 <xref target="WirelessHART"/>have been deployed in the most critical cases to
	cope with the lack of open standards, but those yield a high cost in OPEX
	and CAPEX and are limited to very few industries, e.g., concerts and racing.
	This is now changing.
	<list>
	   <t>IMT-2020 has recognized Ultra-Reliable Low-Latency Communication
	   (URLLC)as a key functionality for the upcoming 5G. </t>
	   <t>IEEE 802.11 is integrating real-time applications in the charter of
	   the	Extreme High Throughput (EHT) Task Group (to be formed at the time
	   of this writing), and</t>
	   <t>the IETF has designed an IPv6 stack <xref target="I-D.ietf-6tisch-architecture"/> for IEEE Std. 802.15.4
	   TimeSlotted Channel Hopping (TSCH) and an architecture that enables 
	   Predictable and Available Wireless (PAW) communications on a shared MAC
	   .
	   </t>
	</list>
	</t>
    <t>
	Achieving Determinism requires a tight control of the physical resources, 
	and at the physical level, wireless and wired are fundamentally
	different. Wireless operates in a shared medium, and the quality of the 
	transmission is fuzzy and depends of variable in the time, the spatial and
	the frequency domains. It results that while the generic Problem Statement
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-problem-statement"/> for DetNet applies to
	the wireless medium as well as to wires, the methods to achieve Predictable
	and Available Wireless communications will necessarily differ from those
	used to support Time-Sensitive Networks in the wired environment.
	The expectation is that PAW would centralize the work on efforts that 
	inherit from DetNet but focus on wireless. 
	</t>
    <t>
    This draft extends the <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-use-cases">
	"Deterministic Networking Use Cases"</xref> and describes a number of
	additional use cases which require deterministic flows over wireless links
	and possibly complex multi-hop paths.
    </t>

 
</section>



<section title="Pro Audio and Video">
   
   <section title="Use Case Description">
   		<t> 
   			The professional audio and video industry ("ProAV") includes:
   			<list style="symbols">
                <t>
                    Gaming (e.g., Play Station, Xbox)
                </t>
                <t>
                    Public address, media and emergency systems at large venues (airports, 
                    stadiums, train stations, churches, theme parks).
                </t>
                <!-- Cinema
				Live sound 
				Music and film content creation
				-->
            </list>
   		</t>
   		
   		<t>
   			Today the ProAV applications are moving towards packet-based 
			technology to introduce routing features and to reduce costs.
   		</t>
   </section>    
   
   
   <section title="Specificities">     
       <t> 
       		Considering the uninterrupted audio or video stream, a potential packet losses 
       		during the transmission of audio or video flows cannot be tackled by re-trying 
       		the transmission, as it is done with file transfer, because by the time the 
       		packet lost has been identified it is too late to proceed with packet 
       		re-transmission.
       </t>
    </section>
    
   <section title="Asks for PAW">     
       <t> 
       </t>
    </section>
</section>



<section title="Amusement Parks">
   
   <section title="Use Case Description">
   		<t> The digitalization of Amusement Parks is expected to decrease significantly
       		the cost for maintaining the attractions. By monitoring in real-time
       		the machines, predictive maintenance will help to reduce the repairing cost
       		as well as the downtime. Besides, the attractions may use wireless
       		transmissions to interconnect sensors and actuators, to privileged
       		reconfigurability, and standardization.
   		</t>
   
   		<t> Using wireless devices also aim to enable novel high-value services.
       		VIP tickets are nowadays more and more popular. Wireless wearable devices
       		may help to reduce the operating costs <xref target="disney-VIP"/> and
       		increasing the number of charged services provided to the audience (VIP
       		tickets, interactions, etc.)
   		</t>
   </section>    
   
   
   <section title="Specificities">
   	   		       
       <t> Amusement parks comprise a variable number of attractions, mostly outdoor.
           The tourists are free to move from an attraction to another, covering a large
           geographical area.
       </t>
       
       <t> We make a distinction between the wireless devices which control the attractions,
           and the wearable devices owned by the visitors. The park may "guide" the
           different users according to the attractions' attendance, waiting time,
           preferences of the users, distance of the attraction.
       </t>
    </section>
       
       
   <section title="Applications">
       
       <t> Tourist attractions may comprise a large set of sensors and actuators, which
           react in real time. Typical applications (ordered by criticality in
           descending order) are:
       </t>
       <t>
           <list style="symbols">
               <t>emergency: safety has to be preserved, and MUST stop the attraction
                   when a failure is detected;</t>
               
               <t>real-time control: real-time applications embedded in the attraction
                   need to trigger an action when an event is detected. For instance, a
                   photograph can be taken when a car crosses an actuator, combined
                   with a wireless ID that the tourists wear;</t>
               
               <t>predictive maintenance: statistics are collected to predict the
                   future failures, or to compute later more complex statistics about
                   the attraction's usage, the downtime, its popularity, etc. </t>
               
           </list>
       </t>
   </section>
       
	   
   <section title="Asks for PAW">     
       <t> 
       </t>
    </section>
	
</section>



<section title="Wireless for Industrial Applications">
   
   <section title="Use Case Description">
   		<t> 

   		</t>
   		
   </section>    
   
   
   <section title="Specificities">     
       <t> 
       </t>
    </section>
	
   <section title="Asks for PAW">     
       <t> 
       </t>
    </section>
    
</section>


</middle>

<back>

<!--
   <references title="Normative References">
 </references>
--> 

 <references title="Informative References">
 
 
	   
	  <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-problem-statement'?>
	  <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-use-cases'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-6tisch-architecture'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-architecture'?>
	   
 
       <reference anchor="disney-VIP" target="https://www.wired.com/2015/03/disney-magicband/">
           <front>
               <title>Disney's $1 Billion Bet on a Magical Wristband</title>
               <author>
                   <organization>Wired</organization>
               </author>
               <date year="2015" month="March"/>
           </front>
       </reference>
	   
	   
       <reference anchor="ISA100" target="https://www.isa.org/isa100/">
         <front>
            <title>ISA100, Wireless Systems for Automation</title>
            <author>
               <organization>ISA/ANSI</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference>
	  
	  
      <reference anchor="WirelessHART">
         <front>
            <title>Industrial Communication Networks - Wireless Communication Network and Communication Profiles - WirelessHART - IEC 62591</title>
            <author>
               <organization>www.hartcomm.org</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2010" />
         </front>
      </reference>
	  
	  
      <reference anchor="IEEE802154">
         <front>
            <title>IEEE Std. 802.15.4, Part. 15.4: Wireless Medium Access
            Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications for Low-Rate
            Wireless Personal Area Networks
            </title>
            <author>
               <organization>IEEE standard for Information Technology</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
         </front>
      </reference>
	  
	  
	  
	   
 </references>

 
 
  
 
</back> 
</rfc>
